A Guide to the Regulatory Case Files of the Virginia State Board of Education, 1988-2007
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Regulatory Case Files of the Virginia State Board of Education, 1988-2007
The Library of Virginia
43483
2 cu. ft. (2 boxes)
Virginia. State Board of Education
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 43483 was transferred by the Virginia Dept. of Education, 12 October 2007.
Biographical/Historical Information
The development of the Dept. of Education began in 1870 when Dr. William H. Ruffner was elected by the General Assembly to be the first Superintendent of Public Instruction. At the end of its first 50 years, the department had less than 20 staff members. In 1928, the Superintendent was first appointed by the governor. Staff size was expanded to in order to meet the increased need for services including the purchase of textbooks, libraries, and general buildings services. The Commonwealth of Virginia is divided into school divisions, each of which has a school board. Each locality appoints a Division Superintendent using criteria established by the State Board of Education.The mission of Virginia's public education system is to educate students in the fundamental knowledge and academic subjects that they need to become capable, responsible, and self-reliant citizens. The mission of the Virginia Board of Education and the Superintendent of Public Instruction, in cooperation with local school boards, is to increase student learning and academic achievement.
The mission of Virginia's public education system is to educate students in the fundamental knowledge and academic subjects that they need to become capable, responsible, and self-reliant citizens. The mission of the Virginia Board of Education and the Superintendent of Public Instruction, in cooperation with local school boards, is to increase student learning and academic achievement.
The Department of Education has responsiblities in adult education, teacher cerftification, financial assistance, and administrative and advisory services to school divisions. The Department is operated by a superintendent who is appointed by the governor. The Department's activities are supervised by a Board of Education, which consists of nine members appointed by the Governor. The Board of Education is the governing and policy-making body for the Virginia system of public elementary and secondary education. It focuses on accountability, evaluation, state testing and assessment programs, curriculum, and teacher education. The Superintendent of Public Instruction serves as Secretary of the Board.
Scope and Content
Regulatory case files, 1988-2007 (2 cu. ft.) document the board's involvement in the process to establish regulations for the Virginia Dept. of Education as part of the Virginia Administrative Code. The series consists of drafts, correspondence, memoranda, and other materials related to the establishment of regulations.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the original order.
Contents List
- Regulatory case files, 1988-2007.
  - Technology standards for instructional personnel, 1997. (Box 1)
  - Literary Fund, 1997. (Box 1)
  - Licensure regulations for school personnel, 1988. (Box 1)
  - Accreditation standards, 1997. (Box 1)
  - Management of student scholastic records, 1988. (Box 1)
  - Secondary school transcripts, 1988. (Box 1)
  - Classification of expenditures, 1988. (Box 1)
  - Contractual agreements with professional personnel, 1993. (Box 1)
  - Employment of professional personnel, 1994. (Box 1)
  - Operators of proprietary schools, 1990. (Box 1)
  - Special education program standards, 1993. (Box 1)
  - Criteria to identify toxic art materials, 1988. (Box 1)
  - Reporting acts of violence and substance abuse in schools, 1992. (Box 1)
  - Research involving students, 1994. (Box 1)
  - Fees and charges, 1995. (Box 1)
  - Licensure regulations for school personnel, 2001. (Box 2)
  - Licensure of school personnel technical amendments, 2005. (Box 2)
  - Pupil transportation, 2003. (Box 2)
  - Special education programs for children with disabilities, 2002. (Box 2)
  - Adult high school programs, 2005. (Box 2)
  - Procedure for adjusting grievances, 2005. (Box 2)
  - Standards for accrediting public high schools, 2000. (Box 2)
  - Repeals, 2004. (Box 2)
  - Classification of expenditures, 2004. (Box 2)
  - Driver education, 2004. (Box 2)
  - Operation of proprietary schools and issuing of agent permits - repeal, 2007. (Box 2)
  - General educational development certificates, 2004. (Box 2)
  - Employment of professional personnel, 2003. (Box 2)
  - Reduction of state aid, 2007. (Box 2)
  - Substitute teachers, 2001. (Box 2)
  - Determination of critical teacher shortage areas, 2002. (Box 2)
  - Re-enrollment in public schools of children in the custody of the Virginia Dept. of Juvenile Justice, 2006. (Box 2)
  - Operation of private day schools for students with disabilities, 2004. (Box 2)
  - General achievement of diploma, 2005. (Box 2)
  - Scoliosis screening program, 2005. (Box 2)
  - Conducting division level academic reviews, 2006. (Box 2)